<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Elijah's epitaph and the motto of all mortalls in the other reason in the text, perswading him into a willingness to dye, in these words, I am no better then [sic] my fathers, I Kin. 19, 4 / by Thomas Bradley, D.D. one of His Late Majesties chaplains and præbendary of York, and preach't in the minster there, and in his rectory of Ackworth, 1669, Ætatis suæ, 72.</title>
            <author>Bradley, Thomas, 1597-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34264</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14173070</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14173070</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102156</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29117)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102156)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1565:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Elijah's epitaph and the motto of all mortalls in the other reason in the text, perswading him into a willingness to dye, in these words, I am no better then [sic] my fathers, I Kin. 19, 4 / by Thomas Bradley, D.D. one of His Late Majesties chaplains and præbendary of York, and preach't in the minster there, and in his rectory of Ackworth, 1669, Ætatis suæ, 72.</title>
                  <author>Bradley, Thomas, 1597-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Stephen Bulkley, and are to be sold by Francis Mawbarne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>York :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Kings, 1st, XIX, 4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102156:1"/>
            <p>ELIJAH'S EPITAPH, AND THE MOTTO OF ALL MORTALLS: IN THE Other Reaſon in the Text, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him into a willingneſs to Dye, in theſe words,</p>
            <q>I am no better then my Fathers, <bibl>1 Kin. 19.4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Bradley,</hi> D.D. one of his late Majeſties Chaplains, and Praebendary of <hi>York;</hi> and Preach't in the Minſter there, and in his Rectory of <hi>Ackworth,</hi> 1669. <hi>Aetatis ſuae,</hi> 72.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>YORK,</hi> Printed by <hi>Stephen Bulkley,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Francis Mawbarne,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:102156:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102156:2"/>
            <head>Elijah<hi>'s EPITAPH, AND The MOTTO of all Mortalls, in the other Reaſon of the Text, perſwading him into a willingneſs to Dye, in theſe Words,</hi> I am no better then my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND now, after this long Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, I fall upon the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Text, the other Motive per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading the Prophet to make this his Suite to Almighty God to take away his Soule, as it lyes in theſe words,
<q>
                  <hi>Nam non ſum melior Majoribus meis:</hi>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <hi>For I am no better then my Fathers.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:102156:3"/>
            <p>In which words, note theſe four things clearly offered to our conſideration.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>An humble Confeſſion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>An ingenious Conceſſion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>A ſerious Obſervation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>A contented Submiſſion to the common Condition of Mortalls;</hi> namely, <hi>To Dye, and to be gathered unto his Fathers,</hi> all compriſed in theſe words, <hi>For I am no better then my Fathers.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>An humble Confeſſion,</hi> wherein he doth not preferr himſelf before others; but others rather before himſelf.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>An ingenious Conceſſion,</hi> wherein he acknowledges of himſelf, He was no better then he ſhould be.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>A ſerious Obſervation,</hi> moſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally true in all ſucceſſions, That ſeldome comes the better.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>A contented Reſolution to ſubmit to the common condition of Mortalls, To Dye, and to follow the Generation of his Fathers:</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102156:3"/>All theſe foure you may Reade plainly in theſe words, <hi>For I am no better then my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all which I ſhall ſpeak ſomething briefly, if firſt, by the way, you will give me leave to take notice of the expreſſion: It is uſuall with the Antients, eſpecially in the Old Teſtament, frequently upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to make Honourable mention of their Fathers. So old <hi>Jacob</hi> telling <hi>Pharaoh</hi> of his Age, numbers his Dayes and Years, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring them to the Dayes and Years of his fore-fathers: <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.9. <hi>Few and evill are the Dayes of the Years of the Life of thy ſervant, and I have not attained to the Dayes of the Years of the Life of my Fathers.</hi> So <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s brethren, asking him forgiveneſs for the wrong they had done him, and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now he would revenge himſelf upon them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.17. <hi>Forgive we pray thee, the treſpaſs of the ſervants of the God of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> So <hi>David,</hi> upon his Death-bed, giving ghoſtly counſell to <hi>Solomon</hi> his Sonne, in the like termes doth even adjure him; 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. <hi>And thou</hi> Solomon <hi>my Sonne,
<pb facs="tcp:102156:4"/>know thou the God of the Fathers, &amp;c.</hi> So frequently, eſpecially in the Scriptures of the Old Teſtament; and ſo here.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſons.</head>
               <p>Firſt, It is a grave expreſſion, and well-becoming the gravity of holy and wiſe men to uſe; it ſtrikes reverence into the minds both of the ſpeaker, and the hearer.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It adds Authority to that which is ſpoken, and commands heedfull Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to what is ſpoke, with reſpect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, 'Tis for the honour of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors to have honourable mention made of them upon occaſion; <hi>The Righteous ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance: but the name of the wicked ſhall rot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, 'Tis for the honour of Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity too, to be deſcended of ſuch Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors: The <hi>Jews</hi> bare themſelves high up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, <hi>That they had</hi> Abraham <hi>to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> though they were removed from him by the diſtance of many Generations.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102156:4"/>
               <p>Fifthly, 'Tis much for the benefit and advantage of Poſterity many wayes; that they can derive themſelves from ſuch Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and gracious Aunceſtors: By this means they come to be partakers of many great bleſſings, and to have an intereſt in the Promiſes of many good things, both temporall and ſpirituall; both concerning this life, and the life to come. Bleſſings and good things, oft times become haereditary: Pretious Promiſes made to <hi>Abraham, and his Seed:</hi> To <hi>David, and his Seed: The Promiſe is made to you, and to your Seed,</hi> Acts 2.39. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> commends the faith that was in <hi>Timothy;</hi> but withall takes notice, <hi>It was not onely in him, but alſo in his Mother</hi> Eunica, <hi>and in his Grand-mother</hi> Lois.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, 'Tis an advantage to Poſterity in reſpect of imitation, an invitation, and encouragement to tread in their ſteps, and to imitate them in the beſt things: It is a ſhame to Poſterity, and a great reproach, to be deſcended of worthy Anceſtours, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for their faith, grace, and holineſs, and to degenerate from them, and to become
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102156:5"/>lewd and looſe, vitious and graceleſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they become a reproach, and a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to their Relations, and the Stock they come of: The Vertues of their Anceſtors are the great aggravation of their vitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and will be their great condemnation another day: Let us ſo walk in the ſteps of our fore-fathers, that if they were living, they need not be aſhamed of us, nor our Poſterity after us to derive themſelves from ſuch Fathers.</p>
               <p>Thus of the expreſſion: We now come to the Obſervations rayſed out of it: Of which,</p>
               <p>The firſt is, <hi>His humility,</hi> in thinking and ſpeaking meanly of himſelf, in compariſon of others: He doth not exalt himſelf above them, but makes himſelf equall to them that were of a lower ſort; <hi>I am no better then my Fathers:</hi> It was his modeſty to ſay ſo; for he was better then his Fathers, in more reſpects then one: For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, He was a Prophet; and we doe not Reade of any of his Race, that they were ſo: It was an Honour, and an Office,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102156:5"/>that was not haereditary; it went not by deſcent, as the Prieſthood did, in the Tribe of <hi>Levie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, He was no ordinary Prophet, he was a Prophet extraordinary, mighty in word and deed, that wrought ſuch Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, as none of the Prophets did beſides, not <hi>Moſes</hi> excepted: <hi>By his Prayer, he ſhut up the Heavens for three years and ſix moneths, that it ſhould not Raine: And by his Prayers opened them again, that they ſent down Raine in abundance,</hi> James 5.17, 18.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In reſpect of his miraculous Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption into Heaven in a fiery Chariot, wherein he exceeded <hi>Enoch.</hi> He was taken up into Heaven alſo; but not with that State that <hi>Elijah</hi> was: <hi>Elijah</hi> was taken up in a fiery Chariot: And in many other things this Prophet was ſingular; The Lord did honour him exceedingly, and made him, as it were, his Deputy on Earth, and gave him power to doe great and marvellous things; yet ſee, when ſpeaking of himſelf, he leſſons himſelf in his own eſtimate, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring himſelf with others farr below him,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102156:6"/>
                  <hi>Non ſum melior; I am no better then they:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Humility is the badge of Chriſtianity: Heare the Voyce of it in the great Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 32. <hi>Lord I am leſs then the leaſt of all thy mercies. Moſes</hi> a great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the Lord, that was a King in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurum;</hi> yet in his temper, the meekeſt man in all the Earth. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> an Arch-Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, the great Doctor of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> yet ſpeaking of himſelf, ſee how he leſſens him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, If he ſpeak of Saints, <hi>I am</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the leaſt,</hi> Epheſ. 3.8. If of ſinners, <hi>I am the greateſt,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. The truth is, they that have Grace, know they want more then they have, they are enlightened, and ſo ſee their wants, their corruptions, their infirmities, and are ſenſible of them: Thoſe that are voyd of Grace, as they have it not, ſo they doe not feel the want of it, nor hunger and thirſt after it, for it is an Act of Grace to be ſenſible of the want of Grace: And a further Act of Grace, to hunger and thirſt after it, in ſpirituall things. None think better of themſelves, then they that have leaſt cauſe. Empty Veſſels make
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102156:6"/>the greateſt noyſe, and ſound; thoſe that are full doe not ſo: They are the light Eares of Corne that ſtand ſtaring up in the field, over-looking, and over-topping the reſt; thoſe that are weighty with Corne, hang down their heads. In the Phariſee, and the Publican in the Goſpel, you have them both, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. <hi>ver.</hi> 10.11, &amp;c. <hi>I thank God, I am not as other Men, nor as this Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican: I faſt twice a week, I pay Tythes of all that I have, &amp;c.</hi> An empty Veſſell, ſee what a ſound he makes, and all this while, but as ſounding braſs, and a thinkling Cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball: The other, with a penitent heart, and a ſubmiſſive Voyce, makes his humble Confeſſion, and Petition to Almighty God, <hi>Lord be mercifull to me a ſinner: He goes away juſtified rather then the other.</hi> The Voyce of humble Saints in the eſtimate of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, was wont to be that of <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. <hi>Lord, who, or what am I, that thou haſt dealt thus bountifully with me, that thou haſt brought me hitherto?</hi> But now, the Voyce of empty, and conceited Chriſtians, hypocrites rather, is clean contrary: What
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102156:7"/>am I not? am I not knowing? am I not wiſe? am I not holy? had ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited Chriſtian all that he pretends to have, and pride himſelfe in it, that very humour would marr all the reſt, and take away from it all the thanks, acceptance, and reward, in that he prides himſelfe in that, which is not his own, and robs God of his glory; <hi>For what haſt thou, which thou haſt not received? And if thou have received it, to whom is the prayſe of it due? to the Receiver, or to the Giver? to the Owner, or to the Donor? David</hi> apprehended rightly of this, when he confeſſeth, That in all the largeneſs, which he, and the people had given towards the building of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to the Honour and Worſhip of God, they had given him nothing, but what was his own: 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.14. <hi>Of thine own have we given thee:</hi> Of his own every way; For firſt, 'Twas he that gave them the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which they contributed to that pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous uſe. Secondly, 'Twas he that gave them the heart to doe ſo; ſo it was his own every way: <hi>Of thine own have we given thee.</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102156:7"/>If there be any good in us, whether Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, Morall, or Spirituall, it is his own: If any evills, that's our own; and this is ſo much, in compariſon of that good which is ſound in the beſt of us, that it doth ſo over ballance it, that it is no more then a drop of water in a bucketfull, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. To keep us humble therefore, and to make us ſo, look not upon that little good that is in us, which is none of our own; but look upon that evill which is in us, and is truely our own; our ſinnes, our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, our infirmities, our inordinate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, ſinfull luſts, unruly paſſions, and if in this examen, we will deale imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with our ſelves, I beleeve there is no man knows ſo much evill by another, as he doth by himſelfe; and therefore ſhall doe himſelfe no wrong, if he confeſs, as in the Text, <hi>He is no better then others.</hi> If ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a Prophet as <hi>Elijah,</hi> doth acknowledge, <hi>He is no better then his Fathers;</hi> well may we, the beſt of us confeſs, we are much worſe. This of the firſt Obſervation, <hi>The Prophet's humble Confeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:102156:8"/>
               <p>The ſecond now follows, and that is, <hi>His ingenious Conceſſion, That he was no better then he ſhould be.</hi> For though there was ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular modeſty, and humility, in this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony he gives of himſelfe, <hi>That he was no better then his Fathers:</hi> yet withall, he ſpeaks it as ſenſible of his infirmities, and that he was not free from thoſe Paſſions, and corruptions, which humane frailty is ſubject unto. Saint <hi>James</hi> making Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable mention of him, <hi>James</hi> 5.17. yet baukes not that, Elias <hi>was a man ſubject to like paſſions with us:</hi> And this very requeſt of his in the Text, <hi>That the Lord would now take away his Soule,</hi> was not altogether free from blame, it diſcovered ſome infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in him, in not being willing to ſtay the Lords time, for taking of him out of the World: the Lord had more worke for him to doe, before he took him away, as it appears afterward in his Story. But God doth not take the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his ſervants infirmities againſt them, though we doe ſo one againſt another; but where he ſees an honeſt heart, an upright
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102156:8"/>mind, truth in the affections, ſincerity in the deſires, ſeriouſneſs the endeavours, and the bent of the will to be towards him, and to the feare of his Name, he will paſs by many infirmities, and failings in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and lay his hand upon them, that he may not ſee them to be diſpleaſed with them for it, and take notice of that which is good in them, to approve it, to commend them for it, and to reward it; ſuch is the indulgence of our Heavenly Father, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us,</hi> if he ſhould ſtrictly marke what is done amiſs, and deale ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly with us in this matter; the beſt of us, yea, the beſt that ever were, we, or our Fathers, <hi>Noah, Abraham, Lot, Levi, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Aaron, David, Solomon, Peter, &amp;c.</hi> ſaints of the firſt Liſt, famous for their faith and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iety, holineſs and obedience, yet had their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aylings, and thoſe foule ones too, in ſinnes of high nature, ſcandalous and fearfull, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Record, all Written for our inſtruction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot for our imitation: But,</p>
               <p>Firſt, For caution, that we may walk warily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd circumſpectly, and at every ſtep we tread, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ook to our footing.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102156:9"/>
               <p>Secondly, For humiliation, that we ſhould not be high-minded, but feare, conſidering what weaklings, what nothings we are, if God leave us to our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, For admonition, that we may judge charitably of others in caſe of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. And,</p>
               <p>Fourthly, For conſolation, in caſe it may be our own caſe, that we may not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore give our ſelves for loſt, or forſaken of God, but lay hold on Chriſt by Faith, and recover our ſelves by Repentance, aſſuring our ſelves, that the Lord will accept us to grace and mercy, as he did theſe our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, notwithſtanding all theſe breaches in their obedience, he owned them ſtill to be his ſervants, and himſelfe to be their God. He is the ſame God ſtill, that pardoneth, and paſſeth by the iniquity, and the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions <hi>of his people,</hi> Micha 7.18. <hi>becauſe he delighteth in mercy:</hi> He will not Sue us at the extremity of his Law, but relieve us in the Chancery of his Goſpel, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring whereof we are made, conſidering that we are but duſt. Gratious, and preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102156:9"/>is that Declaration which the Lord makes of himſelfe to us-ward, <hi>Malachi</hi> 3.6. <hi>I am the Lord, I change not, therefore ye ſonnes of</hi> Jacob <hi>are not conſumed.</hi> Alas! we doe change, and moſt commonly every change is for the worſe: Which brings in the third Note, or Obſervation ariſing out of theſe Words,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That ſeldome comes the better.</head>
               <p>In all things wherein there is ſucceſſion, this Obſervation is found to be ſo true, that it is come into a common Proverbe, <hi>That ſeldome comes the better; but the World grows worſe and worſe.</hi> It were as endleſs, as need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, to inſtance in all particulars, how this is made good: Take one or two in ſtead of the reſt; When God at firſt Created the World, <hi>Behold, all that he had made was exceeding good; and Man more excellent then all the reſt:</hi> But how ſoon, and how faſt, did he, and his Poſterity degenerate, and fall from their primitive purity; ſo faſt, that in ten, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, they were ſo corrupt, <hi>That it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented God, that he had made them:</hi> and their wickedneſs ſo great, <hi>That the Earth was not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102156:10"/>able to beare it, nor the Lord to forbeare pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of it; and that with ſo great a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as ſweept them all away from the face of the Earth.</hi> And after the Flood, when in <hi>Noah,</hi> God had ſet them upon a new ſcore; How ſoon was this New World fallen back into the ſinnes of the Old, not onely in the Poſterity of <hi>Cham,</hi> which fell off in the very next Generation; but even in <hi>Shem,</hi> that great <hi>Patriarke,</hi> after a few Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, fallen to Idolatry, and to the worſhip of ſtrange gods in <hi>Terah's</hi> dayes, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Abraham?</hi> and who knows how long before him? remembred by <hi>Joſhuah, Joſh.</hi> 24.2. <hi>Your Fathers dwelt beyond the Flood in old time, even</hi> Terah <hi>the Father of</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, <hi>and the Father of</hi> Nachor: <hi>and ſerved other gods.</hi> After God had by miraculous Providence brought his People into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and there ſettled them in a happy condition, affording them all helps, and means to keep them ſo, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue them in his feare, and in his true Religion; how ſoon had they caſt off all, and by their multiplyed rebellious, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102156:10"/>diſobediences, and unſufferable provocations, tontinually renewed, even ſorc't him (after many means uſed for their reformation in vain, and without ſucceſs) to caſt them off, and to remove them out of his ſight, and out of that good Land, that he had given them, and to give them up into the hands of their enemies, <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manaſar</hi> King of <hi>Aſyria,</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> under whoſe tyranny they ſuffered great hardſhip a long time, as is remembred at large, in the 78. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.</p>
               <p>Thus take the World in what <hi>Epoche,</hi> or ſection of time you will; As, from the Creation to the Flood: From the Flood to <hi>Abraham:</hi> From <hi>Abraham</hi> to the ſetling of them in the Land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> From thence to the Captivity, and ſo all along, till the comming of Chriſt, and ſo down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from time to time, you ſhall finde it ſtill declining from bad to worſe, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally every Age worſe then other; ſo that if God ſhould not ſometimes purge the Land, and take away the evill that is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102156:11"/>upon it, either by ſome generall Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as of Famine, Sword, Peſtilence, Fire, inundations of Water, and the like; or by working ſome generall Reformations in it, to ſtop the courſe and current of ſinne, prevayling and over-flowing, if he ſhould not frequently keep (as it were) his Courts of Viſitations and corrections in the World, for the ſuppreſſing of ſinne, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually growing, and increaſing, the World would grow monſtrous, in all manner of ſinne and iniquity; and the wickedneſs upon it would be ſo great, that the Earth would not be able to beare it, every Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of men adding to the iniquity of their fore-fathers, and ſo making the World worſe and worſe. The Antient Poëts had ſome apprehenſion of this, when dividing the World into foure Ages, they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented every ſucceeding Age worſe then the former, under the ſimilitude of foure kinds of Mettalls, every one baſer then the other; Gold, Silver, Braſſe, and Iron. The firſt Age they termed the Golden Age. The ſecond, the Silver Age. The third,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102156:11"/>the Braſen. And the fourth, the Iron Age: Every one worſe then other. Or, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of that apprehenſion, elegantly hath expreſs't it, in few words, to the ſame ſence; <hi>Aetas Parentum avis, pejor nos peperit progeniem deteriorem:</hi> Our Parents Age, worſe then that of our Grand-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, hath brought forth us an Off-ſpring worſe then both of them.</p>
               <p>And as in matters of Religion; ſo alſo in matters of civill concerne, (if we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare) we ſhall finde, that we are much worſe then our Fathers: We have more Light, but they had more Love: We have more Knowledge, but they had more Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: We have more Preaching, but they more Practiſe, more Charity, more Devotion, more Works, without which, all the reſt is but ſounding Braſſe, and we with it, but tinkling Cymballs: Their Love ſhall out-weigh our Light: Their Conſcience, our Knowledge: Their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, our Profeſſion: Their Charity, our fruitleſs Faith: Their Fruit, our Leaves and Bloſſomes, be they never ſo faire; who
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102156:12"/>exceeded us as farr in all Morall Honeſty, Truth, Sincerity, and Uprightneſs, as we doe them in the ſhews of it, and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to it. They would deale juſtly with all men, pay every man his own, doe to others, as they would be done unto: In paying of Tythes, they made ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of it, that you ſhall ſcarce Reade an old Will, but you ſhall finde ſomething ſet down in it for Tythes forgotten. In making Conveiances, they made not halfe that adoe, that now adayes we doe, no more but this,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In witneſs that this is ſooth,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I bite it with my Tooth;</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> And that was Seale good enough. But now, if a man make, or take a Convei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, there's much more to be done, there muſt be long Leaſes, Deeds, Bonds, Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities, Counter-ſecurities, generall Warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, Fines, Recoveries, and a World of buſineſſes, (which the ſimplicity of our fore-fathers never knew, nor uſed) and yet all little enough to ſecure a man from a looſe, and falſe Chapman, and too little
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102156:12"/>too ſometimes. In buying and ſelling, or bargaining, (in thoſe innocent times of our fore-fathers) a man might have dealt free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſafely, and one beleeve another, and truſt him upon his word. But in theſe diſſembling times, that we live in, for the moſt part, every man in theſe tranſactions, muſt deale as warily with another, as if he dealt with a Cheate; and if he have not good skill in the Commodity he deales for, he is ſure to be Cheated, more or leſs: And if the other he deales withall hath not the like skill, he is as like to be Cheated on the other hand; For there is no truſt to be given to words in this caſe, Thus much it coſt me; Thus much it is worth; Thus much I have been bidden for it, ſaith the Seller, and never a word true. Then on the other hand, <hi>It is naught, it is naught,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Buyer, but when he is gone, he boaſteth,</hi> as <hi>Soloman</hi> obſerveth. So that our Saviour was not miſtaken, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. when ſpeaking of ſuch Chapmen in buying and ſelling, he calls them both Theeves, both the buyer, and the ſeller,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102156:13"/>
                  <hi>It is Written, My Houſe ſhall be called the Houſe of Prayer; but you have made it a Denn of Theeves:</hi> To ſet forth this by a Compariſon, there is (me thinks) the ſame difference between us, and our Fathers of former Generations, in theſe matters, that there was between <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau:</hi> The Scripture tells us, <hi>Jacob was a plaine Man, and dwelt in Tents; but</hi> Eſau <hi>was a cunning Hunter:</hi> Even ſo, our fore-fathers were plain men, and dwelt in Tents; plain in their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, plain in their dyet, plain in their apparrel, plain in their buildings, plain in their ſpeech, plain in their carryage and behaviour every way; and above all, plain and rich in the rich Jewell of <hi>plain Dealing:</hi> But the men of our after Ages, (like <hi>Eſau</hi>) are cunning Hunters, they hunt for their Neighbours Goods, for their Houſes, for their Lands, for their Farmes over their heads, for their ſubſtance, for their Poſſeſſions, for their Places, for their Offices, yea, (and where they can have opportunity for it, or any hope they may prevaile) for greater gaine.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:102156:13"/>
               <p>And thus we have made out the third Obſervation to be generally too true, <hi>That in thoſe things wherein there is Succeſſion, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome comes the better: Elijah</hi> tells us, <hi>He was no better then his Fathers;</hi> well were it with us, if we were no worſe.</p>
               <p>And ſo much of the third Obſervation gathered out of this expreſſion of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>For I am no better then my Fathers.</hi> The fourth follows, and that is,</p>
               <p n="4">4th. <hi>Obſ. His contented ſubmiſſion to the common condition of Mortalls, to Dye, and to follow the Generations of his Fathers.</hi> And here, by <hi>his Fathers,</hi> may well be meant, all the Generations that were before him, as well the Fathers that were before the Flood, as thoſe that followed after in the ſecond World, from <hi>Adam</hi> that was firſt Created, to the laſt Generation that was before him, I am no better then they, but mortall, as they were, made of the ſame mould, the Duſt of the Earth, as they were; under the ſame Law and condition that they were, to return to Duſt again: They all had their Pilgrimages here on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102156:14"/>Earth for a time, and in their time ſerved their Generations; their Pilgrimages are ended, and they are dead, and gone, and turn'd to their Duſt; I alſo have now had my time upon Earth in a tedious Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and now I pray thee, let this day be the laſt of it, and this place the end of it, here let me dye, and be gathered unto my Fathers, <hi>For I am no better then my Fathers.</hi> In which words we have,</p>
               <p>His humble acknowledgement of his mortality; and in him, of our own, and of all Man-kind, throughout all Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we, and all our Fathers before us, and our Poſterity after us, All Mortalls.</p>
               <p>It is uſuall in the Scriptures, eſpecially of the Old Teſtament, to periphraſe the death of men departed out of this world, by ſaying, <hi>They are gathered unto their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> Here in this world, men are ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one from another, in reſpect of time, by the interpoſition of many Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; in reſpect of place, by the diſtance of many hundreds of miles; in reſpect of ſtate and condition, by the variety of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102156:14"/>of high and low, rich and poor, learned and unlearned, bond and free, Kings and Captives, mighty and meane, ſtrong and weak, &amp;c. but Death gathers all together in the Grave, we ſhall all meet, in the Duſt we ſhall finde one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Death gathers us all into it's Nett, and layes us up in the Duſt. How Courtly the Prophet brings in the Kings, and mighty men of the Earth, brought down to the Duſt, ſaluting one another, and, as it were, complementing one another in the Grave, being met there, and thoſe that were there formoſt, well-comming thoſe that came after them to the ſame Houſe of Darkneſs! There lyes <hi>Adam, Seth, Enes, Methuſhalem,</hi> and the reſt of the Fathers of the Old World before the Flood. There <hi>Noah, Shem, Arphaxad, Terah, Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> and the reſt of the Patriarks ſince the Flood: And there all the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations of our Fathers ſince them, to theſe times, wherein we now live; ſome of them lived longer then others; ſome of them did great and glorious Acts, in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102156:15"/>their time, and ſo were more famous in their Generation then others; but the concluſion of all was this, at the laſt, <hi>And he dyed, and was gathered unto his Fathers. Adam</hi> lived nine hundred and thirty years, and he begat Sons and Daughters, <hi>and he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Seth</hi> lived nine hundred and twelve years, and begat Sons and Daughters, <hi>and he dyed. Methuſhalem,</hi> the longeſt liver of them all, he lived nine hundred ſixty and nine years, and begat Sons and Daughters <hi>and he dyed;</hi> and ſo of all the reſt, after all the Story of their long Lives, and great things done by them, in their time; yet this was the Cataſtrophe of them all, <hi>And he dyed.</hi> Neither Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, nor Wealth, nor Power, nor Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, nor Greatneſs, nor Goodneſs, nor Grace, nor Holineſs it ſelfe, can priviledge from this common condition of the Sonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> but <hi>they muſt dye.</hi> We ſee, <hi>That wiſe men dye, as well as fools,</hi> Pſal. 49.10. <hi>and rich men dye, as well as poor; and ſtrong men dye, as well as weak; and Kings dye, as well as Captives, &amp;c.</hi> It puts me in minde of a Sage, and grave ſaying of an Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102156:15"/>(from whom I doe not now well remember) but comming to <hi>Rome</hi> in an Embaſſie, he was ſhewed all the glory, the ſtate, and the magnificence of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous City: but it chanc't, that while they were ſhewing him all theſe glorious things, there paſt by a Corps, carried to the Grave to be buried; which this wiſe Embaſſadour obſerving, took occaſion from thence, to ſpeak theſe words, <hi>That not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all that greatneſs, and glory, yet he ſaw, that men dyed at</hi> Rome, <hi>as well as in their Country:</hi> ſo impartiall, ſo inexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is this common devourer of men, there is no Covenant to be made with Death, no agreement with the Grave: It is one of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s inſatiables, <hi>which never ſaith, it hath enough,</hi> till it hath us all with our Fathers, <hi>For we are no better then our Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what need I Preach mortality to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls, whoſe very bodies that they carry about them, dayly Preach unto them the ſame thing; and the ſpectacles of morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity which we dayly ſee, Preach it more
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102156:16"/>powerfully to our Eyes, then Funerall Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons can doe unto our Eares? Dayly we heare the Tollings of the Paſſing bells, calling us to our long home: Dayly we ſee the bones and skulls of our friends deceaſed, rak't out of the Grave: dayly we ſee others following after them, and the mourners about the ſtreets. It ſtrikes me deeply into the meditation of morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, when I doe but look over the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Book, to ſee in the turning over of how few leaves, I finde the ſame man Baptized, Married, Buried: Thus one Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration paſſeth away, and another ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth, and haſteth after it, as we after them, till we all lye down in the Duſt of Death: <hi>For we are no better then our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to draw to an end; I will onely ſhew you ſome Reaſons, proving not onely the certainty, but the neceſſity of dying, that ſo we may make account of it, look for it, and provide for it, and ſo conclude this Obſervation alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:102156:16"/>
               <head>And there are ſix Reaſons which make it not onely certain, but neceſſary, that we ſhould dye.</head>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Becauſe we are all ſinners: And the wages of ſin, is Death,</hi> Rom. 6.23. And in the fifth of the <hi>Romans,</hi> ver. 12. <hi>By one man ſinne entred into the World, and death by ſinne: and ſo death went over all men, in whom all men have ſinned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>The Sentence of Death is gone out againſt all mankind, not to be reverſt:</hi> This Sentence was pronounc't in Paradiſe, and dayly put in execution ever ſince; <hi>In quo die commederis, morte moriêris: In the day that thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt dye the death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>The matter whereof we are made, neceſſitates it, the meane and corruptible duſt of the Earth:</hi> And of this God puts us in minde, from the very beginning of our being, <hi>Pulvis, &amp; in pulverem: Duſt thou art, and to Duſt thou ſhalt return.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:102156:17"/>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>From the continuall conflict that is between the foure contrary qualities that are in us; Of Heate and Cold, Drought and Moyſture, one againſt another:</hi> Theſe being the prime qualities of the foure Elements, of which we, and all compound, or mixt bodies doe conſiſt, are found in us, in one degree, or other; all which being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary the one to the other, are in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall fight one with another, which never ceaſeth, but with the diſſolution of the <hi>compoſitum,</hi> the compound body wherein they are: Where here theſe qualities are in <hi>aequilibri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> equally ballanc't, and in ſome due proportion mingled in the body; there the body is healthfull, ſtrong, of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent temper, and of long continuance, which was the happineſs of <hi>Adam,</hi> in his firſt Creation, and of the long-lived Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before the Flood, in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: But where one of theſe qualities doth predominate, and get the upper hand over the other, there follows a diſtemper, and upon that ſickneſs, and weakneſs, which by the Art, and care of the skill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102156:17"/>Phyſitian may be helpt, at leaſt in ſome meaſure, and for a time, if he be skillfull in theſe two things. Firſt, to find out, and to diſcover which of the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties it is, which hath the predominancy. And ſecondly, How to correct that qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and to relieve the other, which is oppreſſed by it, and ſo to ſet them in ſome equall proportion, and due temper again. But this can no Art of man doe ſo, as to keep them alwayes in an equall ballance, but the qualities being ſo dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrally oppoſite one to the other, the fight will ſtill be renewed again, and the conflict continued, till the one hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the other; upon which muſt needs follow the diſſolution of the whole body: ſo that in theſe very Elements that we conſiſt of, we carry Death about us, we onely ſtay while the one hath gotten the maſtery of the other, and ſo bring us down to our duſt.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>There is a noceſſity that we ſhould taſte of death, and be turned to our duſt again, that ſo our groſs, and corruptible bedies being
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102156:18"/>firſt putrified, may be purifyed and refined, and defaecated from all thoſe dreggs, and terreſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all groſeneſs, which was in them, while they lived here in the Fleſh, and ſo be rayſed again ſpirituall, and incorruptible.</hi> This Reaſon Saint <hi>Paul</hi> gives, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.36. <hi>Thou foole, that which thou ſoweſt, is not quickened, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it dye.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 53. <hi>This corruptible muſt put on incorruption:</hi> but before it put on incorruption, it muſt put off corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that muſt be done by death: <hi>It ſhall be rayſed ſpirituall;</hi> but firſt, it muſt lay down that which is carnall in it; this is done by Death, and the Grave, where the body is firſt putrified, and turn'd to Duſt, that ſo, as the Phaenix out of it's own Aſhes; ſo the body may be rayſed out of it's own Duſt, and renewed out of it's own Materialls, that ſo, becoming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, ſpirituall, and immortall, it may be fit to enter into the Heavenly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations, and to be partaker of the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance with the Saints in glory.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, and laſtly, <hi>It is neceſſary that all men ſhould dye, and be layd up in the Earth, in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102156:18"/>order to the great Aſſizes, the great and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Judgement to come, that ſo they may be all brought forth, together to their tryall, for the greater honour of the Judge our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the greater glory of the ſolemnity, and the greater ſtate of the proceedings in that high Court, and in that great day.</hi> This is the Reaſon the Apoſtle gives of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of all mens dying, before the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Judgement: And in order to it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. <hi>It is appointed for all mon once to dye, and after that to come into Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Some particular judgements we ſee dayly executed in the World, in which God doth puniſh ſome particular ſinnes, by Judgements Nationall, Locall, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall, that men may know, <hi>There is a God that Judgeth the Earth; and that ſinne ſhall not alwayes goe unpuniſhed:</hi> But theſe are but as petty Seſſions, in reſpect of the Great Aſſizes to be holden at the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Judgement of the Grat Day. That's the Day indeed, the Day of all Dayes, called, <hi>The Day of the Lord,</hi> the Day wherein the Lord will be glorified in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102156:19"/>ſight of Men and Angells, good, and bad, when they ſhall ſee <hi>the Sonne of Man</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the Clouds, with power and great glory, and all the holy Angells with him, with flaming fire rendring vengeance to them that would not know him, nor obey his glorious Goſpel, when all Nations ſhall be gathered before him; and all the Generations of men which have been upon the Earth, from <hi>Adam,</hi> to the end of the World; when the Angells ſhall gather the Elect from the foure Winds, from all quarters of the World: and <hi>the Sea</hi> ſhall give up her dead, and <hi>the Earth</hi> ſhall give up her dead; and they ſhall all, great and ſmall, appear before the Throne, and be ſet in two mighty bodies, the one on the right hand, and the other on the left, and there ſtand to heare their finall doome; Thoſe on the right hand, the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Abſolution, <hi>Venite benedicti: Come ye bleſſed.</hi> And thoſe on the left hand, the Sentence of Condemnation, <hi>Ite maledicti: Goe ye curſed:</hi> So they ſhall goe into eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life; and theſe into everlaſting fire.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102156:19"/>I conclude this Diſcourſe with the words of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> upon the ſame ſubject, 2 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 11. <hi>ver. Seeing all theſe things muſt come to paſs, what manner of people ought we to be in all holy converſation, and godlineſs?</hi> And thoſe of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the terrors of the Lord, we admoniſh you;</hi> What to doe? To reconcile your ſelves unto God, to goe quickly, and make your peace with your adverſary, while you are in the way, that is, in this life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you dye, and your ſoule be taken away; to break off your ſinnes by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that they may be blotted out, and not be found upon the fyle againſt you; in the day of account, to make your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts ſtreight, and ready, that when the Maſter ſhall call for them, you may give them up with joy; to get oyle into your Lamps, and your lights burning, that you may be ready to enter in with the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome; to purge your ſelves from all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, by the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying vertue of the holy Ghoſt, and get
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102156:20"/>your ſoules waſh't in the blood of the Lambe, that ſo when they ſhall be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the body by death, you may with comfort and confidence, commend them into the hands of God, in the words of the Prophet, and of the Text, and ſay, <hi>Lord take away my ſoule,</hi> and he may own it, and accept it, and take it into the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Heavens, and aſſigne it a place among the holy ſoules of the Saints in light, where it ſhall reſt in joy, happineſs, and glory for evermore.</p>
               <p>And ſo we have now put up the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets Petition to Almighty God, in his own words, <hi>Lord take away my ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But there is no Petition, but referrs to ſome Anſwer, which leads us to enquire after the Anſwer to this: What Anſwer did the Lord give to this his requeſt? Did he grant his deſire, by taking away his ſoule, or no?</p>
               <p>No, he did not: And why ſo?</p>
               <p>Firſt, He had more work for him to doe, before he meant to take him away: He was to Anoint <hi>Huzael</hi> King of <hi>Syria: Jehn</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:102156:20"/>King of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And <hi>Eliſha</hi> Prophet, in his roome. It was after this, that he had that great buſsle with <hi>Ahab,</hi> about <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi>'s Vineyard, and denounc't a heavy judgement from the Lord upon him, for that his oppreſſion, and injuſtice, which fell upon him accordingly; And as great a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie with <hi>Ahaziah</hi> his Sonne, whom he ſentenc't to death, for ſeeking to the god of <hi>Ekron</hi> for help in his ſickneſs. And many other great things did he, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God took him away. Therefore the Lord would not grant this his requeſt at this time, though it ſeemed to be reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and modeſt, <hi>To take away his ſoule;</hi> he would not doe it yet, he had more work for him to doe firſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, If God had granted this his requeſt now, it had been much to his loſs, it had prevented his glorious aſſumption into Heaven in a fiery Charriot, which ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he had afterward, as we reade, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2. Beſides, the glory that he got upon thoſe two Kings, <hi>Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> in ſentencing them to death for their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102156:21"/>And upon the two Captains of <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> in calling <hi>for fire from Heaven to devoure them, and their fifties,</hi> ſent to take him, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1. It had been much to his loſs, if God had granted him his requeſt, therefore he would not grant it, to take away his life, but ſent an Angell with Proviſion, to ſatisfie his hunger, and his thirſt, and to preſerve him from famiſhing in the Wilderneſs, he had no worſe Kate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.6. and afterwards taken up both body and ſoule into Heaven in a fiery Charriot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From hence I rayſe theſe two Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</head>
               <p>The firſt, <hi>That God doth not alwayes grant the Suits of his ſervants, but ſometimes may, and doth for good reaſon deny them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond this, <hi>That God doth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times give unto his ſervants greater things, then they aske, he out-grants their own asking.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:102156:21"/>
               <p>To the firſt, <hi>Moſes</hi> had a deſire to goe into the Land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> God would not ſuffer him; He carried him up to the top of Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> where he might take a view of it; but he would not grant he ſhould goe into it: but there he took away his ſoule, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.4, 5. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was a great favourite of Heaven, and he Prayed again and again, that the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Satan might depart from him; yet was content to ſit down without an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: And when, at laſt, with much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, he obtained an Anſwer, it was not ſo directly to his requeſt; but onely a generall promiſe of Gods Grace to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port him under the conflict, My Grace is ſufficient for thee: <hi>For this thing I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from me:</hi> and at laſt he obtained this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>My Grace is ſufficient for thee. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat primo,</hi> Grace is denyed: <hi>Supplicat ſecundo,</hi> Grace is denyed again: <hi>Supplicat tertio,</hi> Grace is granted; yet all this while, he doth not gratifie him in granting what he requeſted <hi>in ſpecie;</hi> but granted him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102156:22"/>els, that he in his wiſedom thought fitter for him, <hi>My Grace is ſufficient for thee. Deus non ſemper dat ad voluntatem, ſed Deus dat at ſanitatem:</hi> God doth not alwayes give according to our will; but God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes giveth for our weale, as a Father ſpeaks, <hi>Deus audit miſericorditer, Deus non audit miſericorditer:</hi> When God heareth us it is in mercy; when God heareth us not, it is in mercy too. Sometimes we in our ignorance ask ſuch things, as are not fit for us to receive; ſometimes ſuch things, as 'tis not fit for him to give: In both theſe caſes, it is no wonder, if we ask, and have not, ſometimes we ask amiſs; and then, no marvaile, if he deny us, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times unſeaſonably; and then no marvaile, if he delay us: Yet let not all this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage from asking, but let it make us, Firſt wiſe, and prudent, in framing our Petitions, both for the matter, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of them: To take to us words, and goe to God; to conſider he is in Heaven, and we on Earth, and therefore to let thoſe words be few, but weighty. Secondly, To
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102156:22"/>mark well the returns of our Prayers, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God hath anſwered them, or no? or how? If he hath anſwered them <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> and directly, then ther's a ſpeciall ground of Faith, and farther confidence in God. 2ly. By ſpeciall matter, and occaſion of prayſe, and thankſgiving, <hi>I will hear thee, and thou ſhalt prayſe me,</hi> Pſal. 50.15. And thirdly, Great encouragement, and invitation to Pray again, and to goe with boldneſs to the Throne of Grace, not doubting to obtain like help again in the time of need, <hi>I am well pleaſed, that the Lord hath heard the Voyce of my Prayer, that he hath enclined his eare unto me: Therefore will I call upon him as long as I live,</hi> Pſal. 116.1, 2.</p>
               <p>But, if God hath not ſo anſwered <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> by granting thee, juſt the thing that thou did'ſt deſire, mark well if he hath not commuted with thee, giving thee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els in the roome of it, that may be to thee as good as it, as he did to Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> or farr better, as here to our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in the Text: And then, <hi>If where thou askeſt a ſtone, he give thee bread:</hi> Or,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102156:23"/>
                  <hi>Where thou askeſt a ſcorpion, he give thee a fiſh:</hi> Or, <hi>Where thou askeſt temporall things, he give thee ſpirituall;</hi> ſay, thou art no loſer by the change, though thou have not punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that, which thou didſt deſire. So it is here with our Prophet in the Text, <hi>He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires the Lord to take away his ſoule:</hi> No, ſaith God, <hi>I will not doe ſo; but I will doe that which is farr better for thee: I will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve thy ſoule in thy body for a time, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou ſhalt doe me more ſervice and that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable ſervice, which ſhall be to thy eternall fame and glory: and that done, I will take away thy ſoule and body both, and carry them to Heaven in a fiery Charriot.</hi> Which brings in the ſecond Obſervation.</p>
               <p>2. Obſ. <hi>That God oftentimes doth better for his ſervants, then themſelves deſired, he out-grants their own asking:</hi> Thus he dealt by <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 Kings 3.</p>
               <p>That King had a large offer, and promiſe from Almighty God, <hi>That let him aske what he would, it ſhould be given him,</hi> 1 Kings 3.5.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102156:23"/>
                  <hi>He asked Wiſedom that he might be able to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern that mighty people committed to his charge.</hi> The Lord was ſo well pleaſed that he had asked this thing, that he tells him, <hi>That he hath not onely given him that which he ask't; but he alſo gave him that which he had not asked, Riches, and Honour, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 13. <hi>and that in ſuch abundance, that no King ever had the like, nor ſhould have after him. Jacob</hi> being to take a long Journey, through dangerous wayes, into a ſtrange Country, and being but ill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided with <hi>viaticum</hi> for ſuch a Journey, beggs of God, <hi>That he would but grant him food and rayment,</hi> and he ſhould be happy; he askes no more: <hi>Oh if God will but give me Bread to eat, and Rayment to put on, how thankfull ſhall I be for it?</hi> And if you look but a little farther in the Story, to the 32. Chapter, you ſhall finde how abundantly God anſwered his requeſt, with meaſure run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning over, preſt down, and ſhaken together; He gave him not onely <hi>Food and Rayment</hi> in his Journey, but Wealth, and Honour, and Riches in abundance, as he doth thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>O Lord, I am leſs
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102156:24"/>then the leaſt of all thy mercies, for with my ſtaffe came I over this bridge, and loe, thou haſt made me two bands;</hi> ſo farr doth his bounty exceed our very hopes and expectations. As in <hi>Jael</hi>'s entertainment of <hi>Siſera, Judges</hi> 5. <hi>He asked Water, and ſhe gave him Milke.</hi> And as <hi>Naaman</hi> to <hi>Gebazi, He asked him one change of Rayment, and one Talent of ſilver; nay,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>take two.</hi> Such is the bounty of our Heavenly Father, that giveth abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>above all that we can ask, or think,</hi> Epheſ. 4. We ask temporall bleſſings, and he gives us ſpirituall; earthly, and he gives us heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>He asked life of thee, and thou gaveſt him a long life, yea, even for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</head>
               <p>Firſt, It ſerves to admoniſh us, to give unto God the Glory that is due unto his Name in this reſpect, even the Glory of his bounty, that delights in giving, and is never weary of giving, that loads us with his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and poureth his benefits upon us, an inexhauſted treaſure, a Fountain never drawn
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102156:24"/>dry, but continually ſpringing up, with new ſupplies of Grace, and good things of all ſorts, to all them that ſeek them, and to him for them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, 'Tis much for the conſolation of his poor Saints, and ſervants, though of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they have nothing, nor are nothing, but with the <hi>Laodiceans, are poor, and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and blind, and naked;</hi> yet, as long as they have ſuch a Heavenly Father, they haue enough, what can they want, that have ſuch a Magazine to goe unto, ſuch a Father to turn themſelves unto in all their wants, and neceſſities, as willing as able to relieve, and to ſupply them, that taketh care for them, and is engaged by promiſe to ſee they ſhall want nothing that is good for them: <hi>All is yours, and you are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods:</hi> What would they more?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Here's encouragement enough, to goe boldly unto the Throne of Grace, (where the gate of mercy ſtands open, and the Golden Scepter is held forth unto us) with full aſſurance, that we ſhall ſpeed in our ſuits ſurely, and if we have not, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102156:25"/>we ask not; and if we ask and have not, it is becauſe we ask amiſs.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Let this teach us wiſedom, and good manners too, in all our ſuits, never to put them up, but with ſubmiſſion to his will: If Chriſt the Sonne of God did ſo, well may we ever put in, or at leaſt <hi>tacitly</hi> imply, <hi>Not my will, but thy will be done:</hi> Beware of limiting the holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or preſcribing what he ſhall give, or in what meaſure, or when, or how, or in what manner he ſhall anſwer our ſuits; he may deny, delay, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute, give leſs then we ask, or more, and all in great wiſedom too, and upon good reaſon. The Diſciples ſeeing Chriſt now riſen from the dead, and thereby having ſuch an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment of his power and glory, will needs know, <hi>Whether now he will reſtore the Kingdom to</hi> Iſrael, which the <hi>Romans</hi> had lately taken from them, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.6, 7. And the two fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites, <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> expecting ſuch a Kingdom now to be ſet up, put in betimes, and beſpake high places under him in it; <hi>That the one may ſit on his right hand, and the other on his left in this Kingdom,</hi> (though
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:102156:25"/>it was their Mother, which they put upon it, to preferr the Petition;) yet that they had a hand in it, appeareth by the indignation the reſt of the Diſciples took againſt them for this their ambition: Chriſt lik't neither of theſe ſuits, and therefore anſwers both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; To the former, <hi>Non eſt veſtrum:</hi> To the latter, <hi>Non eſt meum:</hi> To the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>It is not for you to know the times, and the ſeaſons, which the Father hath kept in his own power:</hi> To the latter, <hi>To ſit on my right hand, and on my left, is not mine to give; but it ſhall be given to thoſe, for whom it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared,</hi> Mat. 20.23. Again, in other caſes, he is pleaſed to over-grant the Petitions of his ſervants, and to give them abundantly, beyond their own asking, as in the inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces before given, and in the Text, The Lord doth not immediately take away the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſoule, at his requeſt, but reſerves it in his body for a time, till they had done ſome more work, which he had for them to doe; And then <hi>he takes up both his ſoule and body, in a wonderfull manner into Heaven, in a fiery Charriot,</hi> 2 Kings 2.11.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:102156:26"/>
               <p>I conclude this Petition of the Prophet, and my diſcourſe upon it, in the words of the Prayer of the Church, ſet forth, and commended to us, in our deſpiſed Liturgy, as the concluſion of the Prayers of the ſecond Service.</p>
               <p>O <hi>Lord, which knoweſt our neceſſities before we ask; and our ignorance in asking; we beſeech thee have compaſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our infirmities, and thoſe things which for our blindneſs we cannot ask; or, for our unworthineſs we dare not, vouchſafe to give us, for the worthineſs of thy Sonne Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, to whom with thee, and the holy Spirit, three Perſons, and one God bleſſed for ever, he all Honour and Power, Prayſe and Glory (as is moſt due) for evermore,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:102156:26"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
